All right everybody welcome.
Welcome to build twenty fifteen what's going to get started on the session here.
my name is tony penalty now I'm a program manager on the operating systems
...microsoft and with me today is going to be
adam wilson who's going to be helping out with some of the demos.
We're talking about in today's session is user data, you know,
it's good to get an idea from the audience about like how you know-how informed you
are on this stuff how a useful
this is to-you so let's go and get a show of hands-on who uses contacts.
Okay, how about text messages and phone calls anybody
...email and calendar okay,
so, it sounds like this is going to be relevant to you guys so hopefully we got some very
interesting things that are going to enable you to do some really cool things on the universal windows platform?
Just a reminder at the end of the session we're going to be having a evaluation thing so,
I'll ask you that the...fill that out and one last thing to look at before we really dive into this is the application
model map you may have seen this already and andrew clinics or one of the
other talks that have already happen but my team is the application model
on for windows universal apps.
And, what this means is where the team that's responsible for the execution environment and
deployments so, a lot of the basic
wghooks for apps so what you're in right now is the user data section?
You'll have the chance after this one to go to the store and
deployment sections or tomorrow you can catch the app section or
...services section later in the day tomorrow.
User data so key to so many experiences across modern devices and
when I'm talking about user data today what I'm specifically talking about
are the data types of appointments?
Contacts
email text messages calls.
And, user data accounts what we mean by user data accounts are basically like
email accounts away to grouped together so several of the different data types.
Everything that I'm talking about today is going to be available on the universal windows
platform in fact most of it is already available and will be showing you on the tools that you
had a made available for download yesterday afternoon?
A few the cases will only work on the windows ten mobile but that's the
case of like text messages and phone calls which are only support on mobile devices.
When we built these though we expanded what you had available to
you and windows phone store a point one apps?
Everything that was available for windows phone store a
point one apps is now available on the universal windows platform.
Everything that was available in the windows store eight-point one apps
is now available for the universal windows platform and we've added so much more.
One of our goals in this release was to make sure that are great first party
experiences that ship with windows in-box things like the people hub outlook
mail-in calendar the messaging app the phone dialing out core
tunnel all of these apps rely so heavily on user data in order to
enable experiences for the end-user and they're built on
these same api that I'm going to be talking about today.
So, the types of scenarios that we're trying to enable.
This falls into sort of three buckets although these are going to be pretty
loose user data is a huge broad area and all kinds of things can be enabled here
but we want to make search possible to provide core functionality those are
things like contact applications messaging applications
email calendar and dollar applications as I just mentioned we built the first
part experiences outlook mail-in calendar which you've seen all these previews
in the key notes today and yesterday those are built on the same api that I'm talking about here.
We want to make a possible for-you to expand networks and your application.
...scenario and that cases to read the
users contact data and figure out which people the user knows about
the you already know about your service this allows you to provide instant gratification when
a user downloads and installs your application saying hey I already know about so-and-so
you want to messages person voip this person whatever it is
Who knows we want to make it super easy to initiate communication from your applications even if you're not one of
these core experiences so we have a bunch of what we call tasks api
is that allow you to quickly get some sort of task accomplish things like sending
...sms sending e-mail adding appointments etc?
We also want to make a possible for-you to add your network to the core experiences so this
isn't just about reading user data but supplying user data as well.
If you're application knows about contact data or appointment data we
want-to make sure that you can write this into the system.
And, the same place that any of the first party experiences are looking for that so
that your application can show up across the windows ecosystem whether that is
in those inbox experiences and other applications that are written value as well.
Finally we...make sure it's possible to innovate and this is what I meant by this
or just a broad term so what we mean by that these aren't just specific api
that accomplish exact scenarios that we think that you want to do this is about enabling
you to do things with this data there are thousands literally the over a thousand
interfaces that we've introduced in these areas in order to accomplish.
Everything that needs to be done around user data we hope.
Instead of tying to specific use
cases and scenarios we allow make sure that we allow you to do things like build-up your
own data models to bring the data into your own system and keep up-to-date
with that data and we hope that this allows you to do innovative things
in the same manner that outlook mail-in calendar has been able to the same manner that core
...been able to an when it reads the data and actually makes a copy of some
...data in order to do with speech engines.
All of these things require the ability to keep up to date and
...going through that in-depth today.
So, that's a lot that's a lot of promise and that would be a so much to talk about
they said a thousand different interfaces I could rattle those often maybe finish...an hour
so what we're going to do is we're going to focus instead on one specific data
tight and that's going to be contacts we're going to walk through all the different features that we
have enabled and the contact space which
is a superset of the features for all the different areas.
And, then we'll be sure to call out how these different feature sets apply to the other data types
also so that, you know, when where you can also do the same thing for appointments or
for...messages etc in order to demo this we built
two different demo apps that we're going to be showing off and...be helping with showing off today?
One of those is a contact display application so in this case this is something
that's reading the contacts database and...showing that information to the end-user like you see in
the screenshot here so basically just a list view and then when you tap on an individual
contact you're going to additional profile information quite straightforward?
The other application is going to be more of a
network provider simulator sounds fancy all that means is writing contact
into the system that can be read by other applications and show up
in all the other experiences that rely on contacts so that includes the people
...outlook, outlook mail the messaging app
...and all the other cases where we use this contact data across the system.
Both of these are windows apps.
They're both built on the universal windows platform which means that you
can build once and you can...run them across all the family of windows ten
devices whether that's windows desktop and mobile today.
Or soon xbox coyote and hollow...
And, finally as I mentioned will be calling out the different features and.
Let's get going and...the first feature area here.
So, the tasks areas these are the ones that I mention are
for let's say the more broad use case.
These are for anybody that wants to interact with this data but does not want to build your own
ui around it or deal with direct programmatic database access and
these cases these are very scripted scenarios they allow you to do very specific
things and we have several of these so I'm going to go a little bit quickly through these but I invite
you catch the talk from last year where I covered some of these more
in-depth or there's a lot of these since they were available previously on windows phone
eight-point one and for a subset of them windows eight-point one
there is a lot of information already about out there are available...msdn another sources so for
appointments we have six different tasks that we allow you to do we allow you to add a new
appointment in this case what you do is you define a subject and details
time duration and then you pass this into a single api call and then you
...brought up by the outlook calendar app...the user can save...to a calendar or choose to cancel.
Same idea with remove it shows the
...and the user can choose to remove that particular point
...cancel replacing replaces new
is the same thing as ad but it allows the user to make changes before saving...the calendar.
Details will show the actual appointment details
for a particular appointment so this is going on to the page where
then you can do things like the user can modify the
appointment user can delete it from that page all kinds of things and finally we have the
...frame allows you to say hey I want to present to the
...calendar for this day this time and this allows you to do scenarios like if
you're doing may be booking appoint booking tickets or for concerts or things like that it's
great to be able to show the user their own calendar aso that they're able to find the time that's good for them.
Next we have calls so this is another straightforward...the past on windows phone devices we've
allowed you to initiate phone calls but there was an interstitial dialogue that said hey you want
allow this app to make the calls that's no longer the case your now
...to initiated phone call without a user prompt.
And, were okay with this for the end-user because it does bring up first party
...the...progress call dialogue will be the same one the users used to from whenever they may
calls otherwise and it's a very straightforward easy api to use will be...you that one bit.
Next there are contacts so we have three different tasks that you can enable for
contacts.
These three tasks...to bring up the profile card and you can bring that up based
on data that you have whether that's an email dresser phone-number or even a contact
id or you can build a profile car just from blank data that doesn't necessarily match with somebody in
your the context database we have.
The...contact card.
This is something new that's available on windows ten desktop devices.
So, there's many contact card is something that will show up across all different experiences
...windows whether you're coming from outlook mail or from the
messaging app or another other your applications calling them many contact card.
This experience allows the user to easily
initiate a communication mode modality
...communication choice with a particular user a particular person in their
contacts database and we can see on this as
...lincoln xbox listed there so there's different choices you can half and those are actually
different tabs too so that's for messaging...you see right there
then those be able to make voice calls are video calls or sending e-mail messages a
little bit later today I'm show you how to make it so that your application shows up
there right alongside all the microsoft applications.
Finally for contacts we have
the contact picker this is a straightforward concept most people probably who are views the
...before familiar with we bring up first are
...users able to select one or more contacts and then they say
okay we return back to your application and
your application gets the contact information that the user out selected in order to use for really
anything think invite scenarios is a very common situation for that.
We have the email api so this was something that was introduced
this particular email api was introduced in windows phone eight-point one it's the same one
...you to send emails with attachments added to it
and works again across the windows ten family of devices.
Being able to...sms message
...very common scenario for inviting people to like gaming situations you want to
get additional users on your platform as a messes a great way to say hey
go and buy one of your friends to come play this game with you or whatever you're trying to do.
And, finally for user data accounts we have api that allow you to bring up the
...ad account dialogue to fix accounts if you find that account is an error
state or...the user whether not they want to
delete an account so again I move through these pretty quick but they're not the core of the
talk here today I do want to call out one more thing though at the bottom of each of these
slides you see this table and this case this table applied to all the different tasks
slides but...going to be a single table for each of the next feature sets as we walk through
on and what we mean here is that sense all the blocks and that table
agreeing that means that those api...ready to go
...available to you they don't require any sort of special permission
or lockdown access for it they do require annals...
of cases a security capability to be declared in order to notify the end-user that
you're going to be accessing certain functionality but they're ready for you to...at any time?
Ok, so, now let's get into the programmatic stuff this is where we start getting
real fun stuff so the read api
as these are the api is that allow you to query user data and
read that into your application maybe that's for displaying the data and
a custom ui here is a screen shot of the people
apple showing how is reading from the context database?
But, it could also apply to other types of scenarios things like making the connections for the
end-user figuring out whether or not you already know about the users contacts whether or not they're
already present...the system in your system...so when it comes to reading appointments contacts and
email data you have exchange active
...data coming down you have card having held out data pop
and imap or it can be data that's provided by other applications using the
right api which we'll get to and a few slides later for
call history and text messages you're able to read the cellular...
Data or again this can be app provided data that's coming from something like
...which is writing call history entries into the database.
These data models are very similar...relatively straightforward if you want
to learn how to use one of on relatively straightforward to move to the other data types but
...certainly optimized for each data type I mean is very there's a fundamental difference
would be contacts you're going to read and a alphabetical order that
sorted by the system whereas something like text messages you're going to want to get back
...a more chronological order so what we think that...great.
As easy-to-use as we can make it while still keeping
...powerful api sets in order to accomplish these.
So, now we have some yellow at the bottom of the table and we would like everything to be green let's get
that straightforward our goal is to make as much green as possible but currently the
calls and email api is require a special permission for the security
capabilities for those so if you work with a microsoft partner
currently you can ask whoever that is to get access if not...come up to me at the end of the
...and we can make sure you get a email address or somebody can talk to if you're interested in...particular data types.
Next we have search.
So, searches...which is just you know,
a very straightforward scenario for searching and we major we
enabled this for the different data types that were needed
...very similar to the windows dot storage search api is if you use those in the past so
should be easy for you...switch over and start using these for contacts you're able to search things
like name email addresses and phone numbers we do support server search at
...global address look up as well as match reasons so that you can show wire
particular search query as matching hit highlighting some people know about us?
For email we support sender recipient subject or body text.
...we also support server search for that and finally for text messages we support searching conversations
or message bodies here we have some right on the slide that's means that
that's actually not implemented we don't have that yet
in some cases it might make sense that we don't have that for like user data accounts,
for example, there's not going to be a lot of them is probably not worth us to build
...infrastructure for other stuff we...to get to it...available if it's
something that you're interested user voices a great place to up give feedback for that definitely.
So, again, green means good ready to go public capabilities
general capabilities available for you yellow means there implement in...available but you do have to
...special permission we might ask you to do some sort of privacy
or user information thing before you actually...the data.
And, red means that's not something that's implemented either by design or something that we just having gone to...
So, like I mentioned some of those specifically
calls and email api eyes are currently restricted.
This is a large part of the reason why.
So, we have enabled the end-user to be in control of their data is very important
that users trust your applications trust the ecosystem trust the platforms.
we have two levels of allowing the user control and
in understanding about the level data access the first one that they see is actually
the second one here and that's a declaration in the store download page.
So, when you're app declares the security
capabilities saying that it has access to one of these particular data types?
And, then it's submitted to the store then the user will see on the details
page this app has access to your contacts so that's the first amount of information that lets them know
that your app is going to be reading that data then if they choose to do so there's these
new privacy settings pages which are available on the most recent flights
that are available out publicly and these allow the users to turn on
and off access to things like contacts or appointments or
text messages for individual applications so at any time the user is able to go and
turnoff access to your for your app to these data types so it is important
that you handle the cases where the user does that and we'll show you how to do that in a moment.
being said we feel comfortable that this is the amount of control that the user should be able to
have and is going to have...windows ten in order to make sure that they trust the platform and
they trust your applications and they're willing to download them and run them experience...
So, here's the same screenshot...windows desktop because this is of course all across windows
send devices.
All right so now we're going to switch over to visual studio and show you a demo showing these three features
...covered here the ability to read data search and then the privacy
of...go and take over your art thank you tony so,
...what we're going to show you here is how you can read user
...user contacts you can search...them how you can use the
task to make your life easier to complete simple scenarios and finally we're going to talk
about through a little bit of how these new privacy settings are actually going to impact your app and how you have to code your
app so to do that he showed you the app but just you have a rough idea what it looks like
all it does is it brings up a list your contacts displays a little bit of information about them
very simple...to show you the scenarios and...were to step through how
it's actually accessing the users contact information so
...deployed out here?
And, but, hit the first break point so this is the first
step whenever you're accessing user contacts what you're going to want to do...going to request from
the store access to the users contacts database so
...access and you can see here what I'm actually asking for is I'm asking
for read-only access to all the contacts on the system...low more details
...access types in a moment but for now what we're doing is we're sort of
...people apps we want access to everything that we can on the system so we're going to requests...access and
then the very next line here is very important I'm going to check to see if that store I got
back was null and that no return value is how platform tells me that if I receive that
nell it means I've been denied access ok maybe the
...the privacy switch maybe I didn't declare the right capability my manifest but
I can't have access to this data right now and it's important to make sure you do this check every single time
you request access to the store because you saw those toggle there it's just so easy for the user to go in
...that switch on you so make sure you check every time because if it may be the
tenth maybe the thirty it's time you do this requires that you actually eventually have that no value
pop-up so let's say we've got access to the store everything's going swimming...the next thing
we want to do is from the store we're going to get a contact reader now this reader
...we're going to use to read all these different contacts at the store
...very similar pattern to windows that storage reviews that before
...we're going to get the reader and once we have the reader very simple we're going to request a
batch of contacts from that reader all right we request that batch
we...for to come back and there's going to be two checks you need to do once you have the batch the first
check is you're going to make sure there was something in the batch that the user actually has friends
actually has contactsthe next thing you don't want to check is the contact
backs that batch status now in my case right here because I'm we're looking
at local contacts is always going to return success but in the case where the user has enterprise
contacts on a server dispatch status could come back with the...server in which case the
user does actually have contacts but we can't hit that server endpoint for you right now so you want to
pop-up something smart to...say hey, you know,...server connection check your endpoint.
So, once you've done all that it's very simple you get
...these contact objects and I just buying them in my view.
...we go we can pop up and there we have it we have our contacting
...now let's say you're uses the type of people who have a thousand
frames on the social network another fifteen hundred on that one and they just really have to share that
...image macro right now with that one friend so to help them out with that
what we do is we provide the search api is to make it easy for you to search their...
easy for them to...context...a little box of the top here and if I start typing and I want to
share...my friend laura start chirping enamourd
...look at how the code works and what you can see here is I'm just going to grab this search
...from the why once I have...search...going to build one of these
contact query options objects this is again very similar stony mention to the windows that storage
...search name space and that's not an accident we really want to make sure you could reuse those skills
you've got from searching before and use them again in this new space so what we're going to...
content query option...pass in the user search strength and we're going to set what feels we
want to query now I'm a general-purpose people
...so I'm going to choose the search all the fields if you're writing email app you may only want to search
for email address the phone tyler definitely passes in the...
only search for phone numbers that's up to you have that control but right now I want to search for everything and I
can so I search you'll see the very next thing is I create a contact reader with
my query options and that's it now I...that very same
methods before you see so you can see here with just three lines of code
I've added in the option for the user to search for context so it's very easy for you
add this whole new feature and, you know, hopefully dot your users a little more and
...we go we talk back into the app you can see...filter down lower?
So, that's all great the next thing I want to show you here is the tasks ui.
Now this task ui it has to be without a doubt my absolute favorite part of this name
space because it lets me look like a genius I can take all this hard work that
somebody microsoft has done some other team I can take it I can put in my...and I look like the guy
...all a great work so...bunch of different things you can do and we'll show you a couple here the first
is...email you can send an...someone you can set body...you can set cc you can set
...subjects and I know a lot of people from looking for you
can send attachments and this works desktop and mobile you can send attachments
added tasha into an email so you see here if I just click on...name there we go
...mean the compose me email I've got my picture greetings from build twenty fifteen.
again, we can do with phone calls for go back to my app or sms text messages
and just going to jump into this...kind of see the code here as I go to send
...sms as much emphasize again just how easy this is
...to add your app all we do here is we knew up this chat message object I
set the body and the recipient and this information comes from the contact object is
already provided and then I simply call chat message manager show compose message a
...with my message so there we go that's a total of four lines of code for lines of code
of added a whole new feature in my app once again just so easy to add these
new things and the other great part about this is already international...you don't have to worry about left to right
text you don't have to worry about what happens when it's a european phone-number versus
a north american phone-number versus australian phone-number all that's handled
for-you by the system it's just so easy to go ahead.
All right.
All right and one last thing I want to show you here just
...have a rough idea what's happening let's say the user decides...many break points.
Oreos...the break points I can actually run my...ok so let's say
you users been using your after a few weeks and unfortunately for some reason they decide today is not the
...whoops...star here.
Today's
the day this app no longer gets access to my user contacts.
So, what they can do is...into the settings...tony just showed you...if you
...out in privacy you go to contacts here and my users
aside from adam he seems like a kind of sketchy dude...of access to my contacts anymore so I go
ahead they foot that switch...two things to note first of all my...the
...stack here and you'll see if I can bring it up it's been killed
...stack so you're not going to have to worry about
losing contact access midway through your apps execution you're going to get terminated?
Gracefully suspended as.
You will be gracefully taken off of execution
...now you'll see my out pops up
detects hey I've lost contact to the store and this is...great because my
...pretty much useless so I pop-up this whole dialogue that says could you please reconsider
and make it just that much easier for users we've actually providing a deep links into the settings page
...they click this button going to be brought up...to that page where they can
foot that switch so hopefully we make it
easier for them that they're going to want to go right in there and give you guys back access...floater
back on again you'll be gracefully terminated and.
Once your app comes back up it has access so hopefully this is give you a
rough idea how you can read access the data and sort of leverage some of the prebuilt experience
that we have the tony's going to tell you a little bit more about how you can manage the privacy of your data.
All right so that was all about reading data searching data now
...about writing data into the system for a while on windows phone we've had the ability
for you to create your own contact data and write that into the system
in a way that shows up for the people have experience
is something that like scape in the...taken advantage of where the download the buddy list from the
...network the right that into the system.
And, then they're set up where the user can then find that data and the people
hub in other places where there used to going for...data.
Additionally and windows phone eight-point one we added
the ability for applications to do that with appointments data as well.
Nowit's possible to do that with ...email and text message data.
This data as than data that's owned by your application but it's
stored in the system and shared by the system.
You have full read and write access to this data you're able to modify the contacts
delete
the contacts or update them however is necessary for that.
We also give you controls on how much of that data your sharing whether that's with the
...the first party applications or with other store applications we would prefer that you
always share the data so that all experiences haven't we understand that there are some cases
where that isn't really the best interests of the user the network or whatever.
This is great for different types of scenarios whether that's apps writing service
specific content if you have profile encountering data that's not available through the
...other networks great to have that all aggregated together
in places like the people hum and outlook calendar application.
...I...said we have different amounts of security that are available for
you to scope access that other applications half.
For appointments and contacts we have three different
...we have full read limited read...system only so
full read means that other applications are able to read any of the data that
you right in the system you're saying you're comfortable with that you want other people to be able to show
that data and do cool things on top of that data?
Limited read is going to be limited to just display data so that means
that other applications will be able to read in the case of contacts your display name
and the photo that is with that particular contact and we thought
this was important because we want to make sure that other applications can build the same sort
of views even if they don't have the individual pieces of data which might be particularly private
the case of appointments that means that they can read things like subjects state in time and
duration so that they can build basic week views debuts things like that and then deep
link into the other applications that they need to for the particular details pages.
...and email we just have to categories...rewrite or system only.
...text messages we have system only available.
So, again, just to repeat on these...color coding here we have these
available for appointments and contacts and text messages are available with just
the general capability text messages is actually a little bit odd though so she called out
here...case of text messages those messages will not be
showing up and the messaging app that ships with windows when you write them what we've enabled
...a way for you to build a new messaging experience that includes both your messages and
sm sms messages so what we provide as a custom data store for
you to write your messages in...we handle things like conversation threading and
provides you data model that you can then render those messages out and your own application
and aggregated wvu on your network as well as some sms messages.
And, then four calls and email these are continue to
be restricted capabilities that require a permission...microsoft for the capability access.
Ok, so, that's brings us to our second demo let's get right back
into visual studio and we're going to show you how or other application actually
rights contact data into the system a way that is then viewable and multiple...locations.
I'm going to switch...into a bit of a different application this is the test bed
...the tonia just should has shown earlier
...simulates another social network which or some sort of application which has a
bunch of data that it wants to write into the system store so
...to just a viewer this is something that is actually going to produce contact data in
...the system store very simple we sort of
a no-frills application here now what we want to show I'm going to show you is
how this avocation creates its own custom store its own custom contact list and then
rights that data in such a way that the other apps on the system can read it...first
...create and app contact store and apparently already exist so we'll just get rid of
that create anyone from scratch all right now to actually show you how that code works we're
...do is will jump into that the code of at apps so first thing is
we want to do it again it's more core request access from the contact
manager to the contact store now there's a bit of difference here you can see at the end this time
instead requesting access to all the contacts on the system...requesting access to only its
contact but it once rewrite access to those context so a little bit of a switch
live switch up here but you sort of see words...where it's going to go now once I've
request access to the store I want to create my own data store.
And, do this you're...create a contact list
...contact stores made up of a number of contact lists and the reason we have a segregation here is
...you can actually split up
in control the security of your information you can have a contact list that is full
viewable every other app on the system and then you have a contact list is only viewable by
yourself and this hopefully will allow you to share just the information that you want to share with other
...to maybe enable some scenarios where you want your data show up in
...people hub but without leaking sensitive data or showing sensitive enterprise or, you know,
corporate data...you just don't want to share with everybody the world so we're going to do here is
going to create a contact list and in this case...call my panda friends?
And, once I've created the list going to set a few properties
on first thing is I'm going to make sure it's not hidden that's.
Pretty simple I want to share this with the world so let's make sure...public the next thing I
want to do is I'm going to want to give app read access full access so
in this case I'm saying every other app on the system it's okay you can come see my data come look at
come use it for your experiences so for read access and for
write access here I'm going to give system online this means the only thing they can common
...my contact list is the system microsoft provided
...raps can't mess with your data but your user can go into the people
up in edit your data if they want now there's also the option here where you can say,
you know, nobody can read my data or nobody can write my data hopefully again these are sort of
limited scenarios but it doesn't make sense...la social networks case where they, you know,
this data is being managed by the contact not by the
users so let's not have them writing to it so again very simple
then we simply save...changes
...contact list and we're ready to go if we jump back in and just take a quick look
how this works I'm going to.
Actually going to do this reset just a.
So, I'm going to add this big panda contact to the system.
Now as I add that big panda contact we jump back into my other app here.
We jump back into the other up here.
And, here we go we see this big panda contact that I just added so this way my
social networking app was able to add some data into the store and habits surface
...another apps experience so hopefully this allow you to share little data between apps and light up some cool
interact experiences for us all right now I also notice little trick here is my contact
your app is actually able to notice that there was a change and notice that something
...the database so tell me give you a little introduction and how that worked?
Thank you.
So, yeah, we talked about so far as able to being able to the re data from the system.
Or being able to write data into the system but...important be able to keep
that data up-to-date you want to know about when the data that you've written in the system has been changed in the people
of you also want to know if you're tracking the
users contacts when they have made a change the
contact that exist outside of your application and the way that we enable this now for your windows
ten universal windows applications is that we provide change tracking
for you that you can use across the different types of contact stores or the different types of data stores?
...gets complicated quickly but we'll try to talk about is at a high-level
how this how this works for you so...
app will tell us when it wants to change track a particular data type whether
that's the contact listen general that are available in the people,
people hub or whether that's your own contact with
the written or any other data types you say hey I want to change track this particular data type.
Then your application and this kind of cases we show here in this
particular diagram is able to write data in the system because it's this case
its own contact database and but we're also
we're able to have things like the people hub
...data into that particular contact list so when the people have
rights the data and we keep track of those changes that have been made sense the
last time since you said you wanted to start tracking changes and we keep that pointer
for-you we persist that pointer across sessions across reboot you don't have to worry about
that you say hey give me all the changes since I started change tracking and then we'll return those
to you that after you've process room you say
hey I accept the fact that I've read these changes
what that means is that you flush them to discord you set them off to your server whatever
...it is you persisted them away where you never want to see those changes again and we move that
pointer for you to that new location and then we keep track of that so the next time
you run your application you're able to say a give-me whatever...change since last time...
So, that's great, you know,
as long as you're want to be able to get up-to-date when your app...starting or when
your app is your...to a different place what if you're apps already in the foreground
so for those cases we have foreground notifications so this is important if the
...sinking down data while you're app is in the foreground you want to make sure you have that up-to-date
and real-time as the databases changing so we provided events and the
type event handlers that you can use to
know hey something changed in the database that's all they say they're just poke events
but that combined with the change tracking means it's really easy to go figure out what
has changed since the last time that you updated your data that allows you to keep the your you
why up-to-date while you're in the foreground there...application is running?
What about if your application not running so we've also enabled background tasks for each of the
different data types that your application can subscribe to
...also find out when there's been changes to those databases the exact same model
as the foreground and reality can use pretty much the same code that you do for
the foreground notifications but this allows you to perhaps
...keeping an app cache of some of the data and that needs to stay
up-to-date all the times this allows you to register for these background tasks and then even if
you're app has not been run sense of reboot or if you're app is being close
...wake you up give you the chance to do what you need to do to read that data to read the change
tracking data and get your state back-up back up to date?
It's also important for things like
live tiles or toasts if you want to make sure that you can update those and real-time as those changes.
Ok,
so, that's important part of each of these different data areas...so we want-to make sure we show that to you...
code also saddam to come back one more time and show you the change tracking as well as foreground
...I'm all right thanks tony so we're going to show here is
change checking on contacts which is a bit of a for scenario but remember this also works on
email text messages things which are coming in live-in you're really,
really going to want to change track especially if you're trying to replace messaging
at you better be watching my text messages in the background updating me with lifestyles and
updating your toasts or you're not going to last long as messaging at so also just give you a
little bit a taste of the windows universal environment we're going to do here is I'm going to...one-star demo
ing here and desktop and just so everyone's aware and clear on
this everything we're doing here today you can go home right now with the sdk bits that we handed out
yesterday and try...at home there's no magic here this is all available already to go there is
one...little caveat and that is when you deploy two-sixty four-bit machine you have to do a
sixty four-bit build you can't do the any cpu built the little bit of a bugged unfortunately in
a current flight but we will fix...time we ship.
So, this is flip over my builds here.
And, deploy to.
...and deploy to device that's my desktop.
All right there we have it so we're going to bring up that exact same
...this is the viewing after we saw earlier and we're going to just take a little bit of
showing how it works and how does...change tracking?
As well the same time we have the same.
In a julia child's on here I'm going to bring up the other a test bed at that we already had.
So, we're able to do here is make
...data store if I add a contact with my network app we're
going to see right away that appears in my viewing app.
And, there we have...one-half...appears in the other app godiva
little-bitty into how I do it so I'll just turn off
...here for...a little the view.
The first thing you do is when you open that store you're going to want to enable change dragging this tells
us system hey I want everything from here on out I want to know about any changes
happen your database and we're going to maintain this pointer
...through...sets or somebody pulling the battery out your app getting suspended your
app getting terminated we're going to maintain that pointer for-you so
hopefully it makes a little easier for you and the other thing I'm going to do here is I'm going to register for this
foreground event now this foreground event is just a polk is just wakes it's a little event I get
the says hey something has changed go check your change tracker so
...register for that now let's jump into that code here of
twelve.
There we have it so this is my event handler I'm doing my change tracking in the very first
thing you want to do is so important is to grab this deferrals here.
We make a promise to you that it well you're holding this referral we will not contact you
are poke you with another event in so you release it which is fantastic I
honestly when I first started coding is app I didn't realize you could do that a and had to do a lot of magic with
new taxes and trying to deal with multi-threaded because I was making...call
but it all goes away magically when you grab this deferrals so remember to do that
so I...my defer all the next thing I want to do is grab my contact change reader
this pattern again...really familiar from earlier when I did that just reading contacts
...contact now I'm going to re contact deltas so same
pattern you're reading a little bit different information so again grandma reader going to
read a batch of contact changes and I'm just looping through them now every
contact change comes with what we call a change type now this change type tells you what
happened to the database that it also comes with the contact that changed so I'm
...switch on the change type here and therefore
different types of change events the first is a create very simple some
app came in decided hey I'm going to stick a new contact in the database we'll let,
you know, and, will...that context data the other type is a deleted
again some context been deleted we'll let, you know, hey,...that from you I dropped from
...database dropped from wherever you're keeping track?
...next type is a modified this is a little trickier to handle in
some cases because we're telling you something has changed so you have to go in and take a look at the
...contact you've got to bit of...see what comes of different in my case because I'm being lazy and
I'm just updating a ui I treated as a delete and...it just works fine.
And, then finally the last one here is hopefully unfortunate case
but exchange tracking lost this should
be very rare but it can happen on occasion that something happens
are database gets corrupted the fungus reset something happens beyond our control and we lose your
pointer in this case unfortunately you're going to reload the context from scratch because the
only thing we guarantee is that whatever you read after change tracking lost is going to be invalid it's not going to be
useful so you see that one you see here I'm just resetting and re loading on my
contacts from scratch hopefully...very rare case but you make sure it.
And, one last thing I want to mention here...sort-of a general
programming on windows thing but when you're using a system...switch statement please,
please, please always make sure you have a default because we can actually
add new values to the enumeration
and later releases and we don't have break a whole bunch apps when we add that
new value because they're not handling the default case so you just make my life a little less stressful I
love it...just handle the defaults.
And, then finally the last thing I come out here is a asses reader a I
...these changes I'm never going to I never want to...changes again so when you save reader dot
except changes we move that pointer to the bottom the list we say hey you're never going to
see these again we promise you that and the next time you go and re changes you're going to see
fresh new shiny changes and then the last thing you want...on your way out is released defer also
...we can call you again if there are new changes that have happened since you went in.
very simple you can see that you can pop up a case where I can keep my
...up-to-date but unfortunately your app is an always...sometimes you get
not in the background sometimes you get suspended so what we do is we
...allow you to from a background task keep up-to-date with changes
to user data and again we want to make this so simple for things you already know angus
...this code I'm going to show for...because it is just so easy if you've ever registered
...task before this is the exact same code all admit I curb this from the wi-fi sample
from windows eight it's the same stuff the only thing I changed here is that line right there I
had a context or notification instead of wi-fi tty or network change
...trigger so again just so easy...trying to make
is low-stress as we can for you to do these things and I registered background task my background task now
just papa toast whenever I see...change the notification store so just
...quickly that are not line will do is bring up my app again.
We will.
Register...background register my background task again what I just showed you that code that so easy.
And, now if I make a change the contact database we're going to see I get a little toast popping
up...you can see...notification to say hey
something's changed my database now little again what contrived for
to for...text messages...these toasting resume important for user to
drive them...to make sure they really trust and really know about the data on the devices changing
now I'm going to switch over tony here and he's going to tell you a little bit about how you can get your
app integrated in with some of the system experiences like the people out.
All right so I showed you these...profile car's earlier on and mention that we had scape
...link can xbox showing up on these and I'll talk about how
your applications can show up here and these marquis experiences where the
...going all the time.
So, we have this concept called annotations
which allow you to annotate existing contacts that are already in the system and
what you can annotate them with is a set of supported operations?
You'll say that you support showing profile
data or messaging data.
Calling.
Or social feeds.
And, then in addition to saying that you support these you'll register for
a particular protocol launch that we have define.
And, now will allow your application to show up on these particular contacts.
So, your application comes along...you scape as the example.
It says I know about the phone number two one three five zero one five
nine does the system know about this phone-number system
responds yes I know about this phone number that's this particular contact you want to
annotated the application so,
yeah, I know how to message this contact and I
know how to audio and video call this contact great.
Subscribe creates that annotation saves into the system and then scape is
...listed on
the profile pivot as a way to message that particular contact.
We also keep track of the most recently used for each
of the different communication modalities so if you...is somebody that
I scape often rather than seeing sim listed there for text messaging you would see
scape list of their and your application would be right there on par with that this applies to both
the profile card which is the full people have experience as well as the
many contact card which is something that I showed you earlier on
...for windows tendesktop applications and it's
going to be showing up all across the windows ten user interface and experiences.
...in order to see a little bit clear on how this
...here's the new outlook
application so when the user goes...types in a particular
contact user can then click on show more which brings up the contact car
...a lot like link experience and desktop outlook,
you know, is used to and here vibe or has
actually registered for contact annotations for that contact user taps on the vibe
...there and we launch straight into the conversation and vibe and the user can continue on to
that conversation that they had previously started or initiate a new conversation with that contact?
...end-to-end experience for the user
and it's great for your application to appear and all these different locations.
So, that's annotations so here's sort of a wrap-up slide.
You know,
we've been work and we've done made tons of new functionality here and windows
...available on the public api sets and
we know that we've built amazing things opportunities for you because the first
party experiences are on top of those and we hope to see some really cool things coming out of the
developer the developers you guys over the next year or longer we also know we're
not done yet this table should be almost all green there should be maybe a few cases of read things
I don't actually makes sense but we're working towards it and we really believe that we're working towards a
places more open and more enabling you to do things with
the user data and these experiences which are so core to
a modern experience whether that's mobile or desktop experience.
So, the final thing please do submit evaluations and then I'll
be taken a few questions for looks like about the next six minutes here if anybody like to bring something up?
Right so it the question is whether not exchange data and corporate environment data will be available through
these api...and in generally speaking the contacts the appointments
data are available yes, is the short answer so that me all
the data is available and, the reading the contacts data yes you have that available
same with the appointment data the email data itself is currently that
restrictive format so that is not available ...will be available through these api seos?
No, ...a...phone calls are mobile only so the question was whether
...consent sms from a windows desktop
application and there is no sms stack on the windows desktop currently so.
When if and
when we enable that in general on the windows desktop we would expect that these api as...be enabled also?
just...follow-up if you're interested in taking a look at how you would detect to see if the...api
...available where you are and the...your running on right now brent...
talks more mornings...have a lot of information about detecting device capabilities and doing a good job
of detecting what's available in where your current execution environment.
I'm sorry I think the question was about social operations.
Yes,
so, that is available I am not an expert necessarily on that it is.
I if you can what's that no nobody does nobody is talking about it out build but,
yeah, if we want to talk afterwards I can get you in touch with a person who know more about that my
understanding is it's mostly...api set brought forward from the windows phone
eight-point one experience but opened up generally available to all applications.
And, it might be mobile only.
But, I'm not...
...and product one.
The so, the question is about duals them and yes the api handle it and,
the case of phone lines one of the first thing you do when you either initiating a call or reading
the call history data is you enumerate the lines that are on the system and those can be
a multiple sims what one or more sims or they can be
our app based and lines that are enumerated.
...the...first.
So, you can for the most part replace those applications
...those experiences on windows desktop on windows mobile they remain
the default experiences and the case with other apps for launching into them but like
for the...new email api that just uses a mail to protocol
launch so that's the only thing kind of making the outlook mail app the default experience so if
you're application has the access to read it then it has all the same
capabilities as the outlook application and when you bring up that if you remember on the
task slides I know there's a lot in there but there was the api that was...
a new accounts that's that experience that you're referring to where the user can go in and set up a
exchange account or a google or I...other...we support and that's what
rights those data in that data in whether that's...contacts or the email...data?
Correct so the question was what does the email app actually talk to exchange server and no,
it's actually system component that talks the exchange server...into the centralize database
...allows your applications as well as
multiple first party applications so one good example that is core
...has done a flight tracking for a while so if that data with
...in the email application core tama would presumably have to
come up with some other mechanism in order to get that data whereas with this sort of
model is available to multiple different scenarios powered by multiple different applications.
I'm sorry I'm not getting that at...nodes change tracking but.
Yes, so, the question was if I is the user make a change in the people after the
contact database will natural for the contacts change tracking api
...so when you say you're registering for the change tracking one thing we
really go into a contacts our that contacts are when you human the people
...what they are...aggregate contacts they're made up of multiple raw contacts a
raw contact comes from one particular and
...network whatever that is if it's an exchange
service or a outlook dot com account like adam I might have a contact
...work contact through exchange and then one...personal through my outlook dot comical
...combined into and aggregate and that's what you wvu on the people hub so
when you register for change tracking if you're doing the opening up that contact
store scope as all contacts read-only...you really reading that are the
...is the aggregate table so that's the table of all the people that show up not
the individual raw contacts and that would be the one that you would want to change track on top of and
if you change track on...anything that changes any of the...contacts that's in that aggregate
table would results and change tracking information for you that you would have available.
The,...theI don't know the specifics of the algorithm it's something we've you know,
between king sense windows phone seven but,
it yes if they had the same email address or the same
...we also check the name and then if all three of those
matches like a definite match and then if we get like one or two pieces of data
...a partial matching we look at other data ...there's, there's stuff in there that
...works in something we tweak...
The back.
Yes, so, that was actually the question about...social, social feeds at least that's what I thought he was asking
...I hope that was the question this question was is they're going to be a what's new feed api
and there is one available generally available to open to your applications and,
again, if you're interested catch me afterwards and I'll get you to the email address at least the people get
your more information.
Yes, so, the question is if you're app is on installed than is your data removed and yes
so whenever you're app of writing those custom data stores whether it's contacts
or appointments or the other ones if you're app is on install we remove that data from the system.
All right and I think...here unfortunately but you have any more questions feel free to come
asks afterwards or we're going to be in the windows insider lounge which is sort of over
...by the windows for the next ninety minutes if you have any questions at all about user
data storage apps anything just come feel free to ask us and we'll try and help you out or at least
...somebody knows...more than we do thanks again for coming
...a lot evaluations if you...like apps five sars samoa thank you.